we will look now at instruction
scheduling in the compiler not that this
is different from what happens in a
tomasula type scheduler where the
hardware is trying to reorder
instructions in a different way than
they were arranged by the compiler now
the compiler will actually try to do a
similar thing here's a sequence of
instructions that can happen we load a
value from the address in R1 into R2 we
add r0 to that we store the result back
into that memory location we next move
the memory address four places forward
so that we are looking at the next for
example element in an array in memory
and then we compare the pointer to some
sort of end of array pointer and if
they're not equal we jump back to the
loop so these are five instructions out
of which a single iteration of a loop is
composed of let's say that we have a
very simple processor that can only look
at the very next instruction so it's not
really trying to have reservation
stations and execute out of order in
that case what might happen is there
would be this load and let's say it
takes two cycles to actually get the
value into this register from the cache
that means that the next cycle the
processor cannot do this add it has to
stall because the result in R2 is not
available yet in the next cycle it will
be adding r0 to the value in R2 let's
say now that the ad takes a few Cycles
let's say three so only here can we
store the next instruction doesn't
depend on the store so let's say we can
do it in the next cycle but then this ad
again takes three cycle let's say so we
have two stalls before we can do this
Branch so let's say that the compiler is
trying to help the processor do better
than this if we still have the same
processor but we want it to execute
these instructions faster than 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 cycles per iteration how can
we do that well what the compiler will
try to do is it knows that after this
load we cannot do this ad until two
cycles later so it's going to try to
find something that can be here so we
need something that doesn't depend on
the load and can be done here now we can
see that the ad does depend on the load
so it cannot go here the store needs the
result of the ad so it cannot move here
but the ad actually can go here because
the ad doesn't depend on the R1 value
here so the compiler is going to try to
move this ad ey here so we want a
schedule in which the ADI is here
because this processor can do only one
instruction at a time in the order in
which they're listed in the program that
would mean moving this ad here in the
program let's see how that would be done
so
conceptually we want this add here note
however that while the load gets the
same value of R1 that it did before the
store now gets R1 that has already been
incremented by four so we have moved
this ad because this R1 is now larger
than it should be we have to fix the
offset here so that it loads from R1
minus 4 when we remove this ad the
branch still sees the correct value of
R1 because it needs to see the
incremented value and the new program
looks like this the black stuff is the
stuff that has moved or changed and the
blue stuff is what has remained exactly
the same as before now let's see what
happens to our schedule now we have a
load and instead of the ad here being
the next instruction so we have to stall
the next instruction is this ad this ad
can proceed in parallel with the load it
doesn't depend on the R2 so we can
actually do this add here so instead of
a stall we can now do our add I this
eliminates one of the Stalls the add
here doesn't depend on this ad so it can
still stay where it is now in order to
get to the store instruction we still
have to do the two stalls because the
add here takes two cycles of stalling
before we can use the result so this
store needs to stay here but at this
point we have already done this ad ey
it's moved here of course the store now
needs to be modified this way so this
instruction is now like this the ad now
goes away so we have just removed one
cycle here next when can we do this
Branch well the add has happened here we
cannot use R1 until one to the third
cycle from there so pretty much at any
point after here the branch actually
safe to go as far as R1 is concerned
note that here we had to stall because
of this so we have just eliminated two
more Cycles here and now we can do our
Branch so pretty much we had plenty of
stalls then now we have only two stalls
and the rest of the loop body is
scheduled so pretty much the idea of
instruction scheduling is to find
instructions that can be done in place
of stalls and thus avoid having too many
stalls in the processor schedule